the idea of regeneration of course
[Music]
starts with Bill and I very much from
your try Aki IFF book with that in the
title but quite separately
it'll found himself drawn into that area
and I met with Edward Muller in
Gothenburg last March and heard about
his aspirations for Costa Rica and the
University and so on and it became clear
that this was was catching on then what
happened was that I was challenged to do
a deeper dive into what our approach was
really what was the essence of it and
eventually I came up with the
repositioning of something that we've
been doing for some years way back that
we call generative thinking and I
realized that the essence of what we
were trying to do was really to help
people generate and so we thought well
if you want to regenerate and you can't
generate that's not going to work very
well so maybe we have a role to play in
[Music]
offering ways of deepening and
accelerating the generative thinking the
is part of the requirement of
regenerative cultures of course we don't
specialize in change in saving
ecosystems or turning cities upside down
and so
but we feel we can play around with the
people who do that kind of work
so um putting something together on that
led to the question of well what is it
about our methods that lend themselves
to that field and what emerged was a new
synthesis that actually we had
components of generative method here
that we hadn't realized knew that that
they constituted a system that was more
powerful than just the parts alone so
that's what I like to share with you so
this is the kind of upfront explanation
and then because it's you I'll give you
a couple of slides on the esoteric
background um since you're recording
this I'll kind of read it through and um
perhaps comment but basically we're
looking at it that the whole earth
strategies can be better generated if a
coherent system of generative methods
are used to orchestrate the wide range
of complexities in the many fields of
ecology society politics and economics
in the Anthropocene and its accompanying
climate emergency this is true for local
as well as large-scale projects so just
an aside here that our our position is
we we cannot be more than just
appreciative of these different fields
we can't be expert in any of them and we
don't you know take large plots of
planet Earth and offer to restore it but
what we can do is look at the
deeper aspects of regeneration which is
that if we can't think that way can we
really do it so this leads us into the
idea of well it's a collaborative world
yet the history and development of most
of our collaborative methods are based
on analysis specialization a dislocation
rather than synthesis
transdisciplinarity and integration this
legacy further exacerbates society's
access to the required role of creative
imagination fully integrated with the
best expertise and data in our
prevailing culture these do not sit
comfortably together in fact when I was
drafting this I was suddenly reminded of
God it must be well over 40 years ago
now as a young scientist reading CP
snows the two cultures things haven't
changed greatly decades of research and
field practice before the founding of h3
unis explored many aspects of how
creative integrity z' might be formed
that are better able to tackle the
complex the urgency and ambiguity of the
current global predicament I'm just
making the point that there are decades
of work by several parties some known
some unknown that has kind of fed into
this work it didn't just start when we
set up the enterprise called h3 uni to
enable effective transmission of these
they've now been distilled down to a
system of five core methods based on
what we call generated methodology we
regard generative methodology as a key
to human processes of transformation
regeneration and integration able to
scale linked from the personal through
the local to the global
so that's the kind of preface so what
does it look like well why is a system
of methods needed um a benign
integration of humanity with the planet
makes demands on all aspects of the
human being mental emotional physical
just thinking stuff just feeling stuff
just doing stuff alone or insufficient
and easily fall into disconnection
alienation and generation of unintended
consequences so the following diagram
represents the span of concerns that are
needed to integrate these factors to
create an integrity so we can look at it
as two large overlapping worlds the
planetary world which of course is the
planet the biosphere the habitats the
whole climate and atmospheric and so on
world of the planet and the human world
which although it's part of the planet
there's a big overlap has its own
peculiar nature of psychological and
spiritual depth to bring these two
together needs a kind of bridging
process where we need to improve our
ability to grasp the complexity of the
planetary world we need to be able to
engage future consciousness in the
present to see what transformations and
regenerations are required and to be
able to envision that and we need the
ability to navigate transformation
through the inevitable tensions and
polarities that arise from what in our
language we call the connection or
interrelation between horizon 3 in
horizon 1 and to do that we need to be
able to do it in communities we need to
be able to evoke the human world as
wisdom
not simply as creatures a species on in
the biosphere so how does that map into
what we're doing well the planetary
world we've developed the world system
model is a quick way into the complexity
of the world human system the socio
ecological system and this provides a
shareable mental image which is simple
but not simpler than is needed to get
our minds and hearts around the
interconnected issues but if we're
looking at say a particular place based
regeneration we need to absorb the
complexities of that particular and
peculiar situation and that's grasping
complexity and we find that the hexagon
clustering methods and things that
derive from that like influence diagrams
enable a multidisciplinary group to come
together and share their um their ideas
and generate new concepts to understand
what's going on then when we move into
the so where where might this go what at
what is the vision of the regenerate
future
we can use the three horizons method
which honors both the existing world the
future world and at under transformation
the meta morphosis that's needed between
the two but then if we have
transformative innovations to actually
address the challenge we come into the
tension between the old and the new
between the horizon one and the horizon
three and horizon two initiatives
triggering pushback and difficulty and
in order to avoid polarizing those as
foreign against for them on us we find
the dilemma resolution method enables us
to better navigate the combinations and
complexities of differing values and
cultural positions in relation to the
change by again creating conditions for
creative insight that transcends these
starting positions of all the parties
but then we have groups and communities
that are taking care of or being
stewards to this emerging world and
wisdom is needed and we've drawn on an
indigenous tradition of the wisdom wheel
of a modernization of it especially for
this purpose which we call the wisdom
wheel so you can picture that if you
work through this bridge from the the
world that the world system we can
develop our understanding collectively
arrive at wise insights and then
navigate the interventions back into the
world and this becomes a systemic cycle
end of speech
you're on mute Daniel if that matters
thank you I thank you I didn't notice
and yeah I think thanks for that that's
like it's wonderful to see the the
methods that you've shared with me over
the years all in this one storyline now
making sense together so this happened
as you were looking at the material that
the Genesis group has put together more
deeply or just in conversations with
Bill in general about regeneration
well builds the one who does the
in-depth study so he was feeding me
distillation which I believe he'd
started with you mm-hmm
you did together I was simply doing my
usual jackdaw approach and plucking out
the shiny bits and and linking it with
you know other background and and the
other background which is what comes
next is that of course I've been doing
this cosmic ecology work and drawing
heavily on John Bennett's systematics
which have rechristened crawl systems
they sort of modernize it and D
connected with systematics in biology so
cual systems has an a transformational
system which is the pentad the fivefold
system so what i've been looking at as
it were at the next level is this kind
of arrangement
now the pentad is a very interesting
diagram which bennett particularly
elaborates in volume 2 of the dramatic
universe and which i used to build the
system of a cosmos as in my cosmic
ecology
and it needs a little interpretation the
idea is the first of all that it's
arranged this way because there is a
sense of level from lower to higher
which lower to higher not in the sense
of a conventional hierarchy but corset
definer if you like and and and so the
outer terms here are that as it were the
the outer boundaries of the system in
question and so we're looking at earth
at one end and wisdom at the other so
we've got earth here as the world model
and the wisdom wheel symbolizing that
then you have an inner active role of
the being in this transformation which
has a higher nature a lower nature and a
center to use the old alchemical word
quintessence from five incidentally
Bennett took this diagram from the
medieval esotericist Robert Fludd FLE
you double D and now I near here is that
this is this is the represents the
beings involved in in in the
transformation so pattern is there
because the the key thing that has to be
shifted at the basic level is the Repat
earning different pattern of life
different pattern of understanding
different pattern of feeling different
pattern of relationship to even the
cosmos the higher nature is the capacity
to transform to actually become that
different butterfly from me from the
caterpillar but all of that needs the
focus of understanding what the future
holds and where we are right now and
what the difference is and what is
needed so you can use this as a kind of
nonlinear system which it goes a bit
further than the kind of bridgie diagram
on the previous slide and go into some
fairly detailed elaboration of of the
system and rather than talk about this
I'll just leave you to you know that
this is this is a seminar in itself but
and it's it's also a research tool
because there's a lot more to be learnt
from investing but what I find
interesting the the quintessence of
future consciousness in this in what I
keep finding as as though the bits of
you're explaining Bennett's work that
most excite me are these different
dimensions of relating to time and
future and and also this notion of reap
happening and the future potential of
the present moment I think is enormous
ly powerful because somehow it takes us
away from the notion that when we use
all these methodologies to get a group
of people together to kind of work on
regenerative cities or regenerative fire
regions that we they're all we're doing
is improving our understanding and
forming some sort of better vision of
the future and strategy of how to get
there but what I see in this is that the
actual process of engaging with it is
already every patterning because it
changes how people think and because
what changes how people think it means
how they bring forth the world together
changes and that's instantaneous and
that doesn't make any sense and may be
very very much because in a way future
consciousness is on this diagram as a
tip of an iceberg be the iceberg itself
is the whole richness of the present
moment and particularly the nested
present moments up to the greater
present moment of the evolution of the
earth if you like so in that present
moment model that I've worked with
derived from Bennett the the the time
dimension doesn't really do it for the
future
all that's only one aspect of it the the
key thing for me I mean you know we're
used to talking about the space-time
continuum or I prefer to use the Greek
words now because of the ambiguities of
the word time and Chronos space Kronos
but there's the dimension of I used the
Greek term io Neos rather than the
English eternity because eternity is
often understood as a lot of time and
it's not it and space ionia s-- is the
pattern bearer
it's the akashic patterns and therefore
the the meaning of future consciousness
that bill and I use is that we're
tapping into the space IO Neos which is
this rich potential I suppose in in old
in olden times it was called the Civitas
day or something like that it was the
the sense that there was a a potential
world that might be actualized that
might come about and trying to shift
this from some kind of religious dogma
into some kind of scientific principle
that this dimensionality does in some
sense of the word exists and then you've
got the the the other the third time
light dimension that Bennett called AI
Parks's which is also from the Greek
meaning abel 'no stubbe sø we can have a
potential we can have an actual the
potential is greater than the actual but
how we got this third factor of the abel
'no steuby to enable it to come about
and that level of coming about is
transformative it's not chronological
it's not one damn thing after another
see this this is wait for me that
because that's always been my I I would
love to engage people in Genesis and
even Carol Sanford who hold this deep
knowledge of regenerative practice that
they've kind of curated as a set of
frameworks and ways of working over the
last 20 years they met so perfectly onto
this because what what like the whole
notion of essence and potential and and
the way that the practice itself unveils
the potential that is already there yes
additively creates it so it's the
difference between what Henry calls
authentic holds and and additive holes
yes but that the essence and the
potential is there but it needs that
practice talk to to actualize it yeah I
mean our our first person development is
a critical factor in the instrumentation
of being able to access and that's why I
did my last term colloquium in early
September on creative imagination I
[Music]
didn't talk about it in
colloquium but I'm drawing quite
strongly on Rudolf Steiners work on
imagination intuition and inspiration as
three higher faculties because without
that personal tuning in the people
engaged in regeneration it ain't gonna
happen or it's going to happen in a very
you know happenstance random way it's
not so the idea that there are actual
practices of tuning in to the eye
O'Neill's future rather than the Chronos
future the colonel's future we need to
look at is you know the planet burning
up you know that that's all very
predictable the scientists do that but
they they can't do the creative
imagination bit and the artists can do
the creative imagination bit but they
can't be practical they can create
symbols and and invocations of
difference and then you know the the the
I know that the permaculture enthusiasts
can can manifest something which is
amazing and draws out the the potential
but because it's not understood in this
wider context it can't it doesn't kind
of scale and communicate perhaps in the
way that we needed to do now I'm not
saying that we've got the answers to all
of that but my goodness me I think we
got a really good research and
development pathway here now one thing
that they also as you were outlining the
initial faith with the earlier diagram I
was looking at I don't know to what
extent you if you've had time to look
into Nora Bateson's work on warm data
and the warm data labs and I personally
haven't even had a chance to look into
it as deeply as I would have liked to
but from what I understand and like I
would love to just take part
one of those labs and sooner or later
I'll create the opportunity out Sonora
in Delfy and in mid-october so mmm
maybe I'll learn more then but my sense
is that the world game and the world
systems map and looking at where they
like in in this kind of fractal
dimension or the recursive et that you
built into the world systems map of
working at local scales at regional
scales national scales of global yeah
and one of the core descriptions of what
is warm data is that it is trans
contextual data and it is valuing the
quantitative cold hard scientific data
that we've collected masses of in each
of those different contexts but then as
far as I understand Moore has created a
process of enabling people to dance
between touching in with that kind of
data from a particular context on a
particular issue but then building up a
multi-layered process of connecting with
these different contexts and then
actually knowing like working with our
more embodied knowing and our more
intuitive and sensing in feeling way of
engaging with reality to to draw a new
type of meaning out of this cold data
trans contextualized so it becomes warm
data and actually is informed by the
wisdom that each each and every one of
us who is a participant and therefore
also an expression often co-create
co-creative agent in the system were
working with yeah I think not I mean I
could relate that to this vertical line
here between grasping complexity and
navigating chance rate I mean the thing
about
dilemma resolution understood more fully
is that you can only resolve
a dynamo or you can only transcend a
dilemma by by let's just call it
creative imagination for the moment and
therefore you have to have a way of
relating the the hard imperatives of the
data with the human capacity to make
meaning and significance out of that
that can you know then establish new
ways of living particular living with
with nature and so on so I think
probably one could create an even ijen
Eric a much more generic version of this
diagram that would assimilate more
approaches and possibly show ways in
which they might relate interconnect I
mean this one is particularly done to to
deal with you know our particular
special offerings as it were so I think
I think that those explorations do just
can you flip flip back to the wisdom
wheel because I haven't practiced I mean
I've worked with the way of counseling
and the wheel of the four directions in
in an indigenous wisdom around that um
for a number of years but but this kind
of these different roles the strategies
the Guardian and so on I'm not familiar
with that version of the wisdom wheel
how how does that run as a process gets
a bit bigger mm-hmm okay well it's
both southeast seven and three and
north-south and one and five East and
West so in that census mm-hmm this is
from their harmer tradition in New
Mexico that David went out and studied
in some depth um David Adams um these
are what they distilled in wisdom
teaching which is far more complex than
this the forum works as a way of
arriving at a balanced and therefore
wise decision so the first thing is you
put your question in the middle here and
if you haven't got a question this don't
work very well you've got it you've got
to have the the need for it so to speak
then it's nonlinear but it does help
particularly when you're getting into it
to treat it as a cycle a bit like an NEA
Graham you go round it so you start with
the genius or a disruptive genius and
this is this is where you have a
question and the crazy idea comes in and
it's disruptive as we know from
disruptive innovation and without that
you don't have a spark of something
different so this is where perhaps the
glimpse of a new pattern comes in you
know we could actually have
heavier-than-air machines that fly
peacemakers
very interesting that it's called
peacemaker because the peacemaker is is
the calm appreciator of what actually is
so it's not a naysayer like we can't
possibly have a heavy the no machines
fly it's more well let's just look at
that I mean at the moment we've got this
that and the other and something else
and we haven't got this that and the
other and something else and so that's
where we are folks
mm-hmm and then you've got the Pioneer
with more they kind of that the role of
well yeah we can fly kites
you know let's see if we make bigger and
better kites or something
[Music]
finding what find a way you know where
we can see something different could be
done that would loosen things up the
Pathfinder is more the view that says
well I can find a way to do that I can
find a route I can find a roadmap for
doing that well then that remember this
is a community - so the thing then is
this this the steward Rory say well I
actually you know there are some values
we have to look at here in terms of
safety I mean you know you're gonna sort
of have all these people jumping off
cliffs with things that haven't been
tried out and whatever it might be you
know let's let's take care let's let's
look at what needs nurturing so this
would be you know looking after the
species in the ecosphere in the habitat
or whatever it is then you have the
oracle role which is um the the
intuition about timing the moment
this is this is this is right for now
this is wrong for now very crudely but
more Maura kind of does this fit the
times and circumstances I guess it's the
Sufi time place and circumstances then
you have the strategist the strategist
is the well if you if you guys are doing
all that you're gonna have to put it
together real smart to actually get
there and so you need you need some
strategic ideas and then you have the
Guardian role which is the well hang on
a minute
we have an ethos is all this consistent
with our values and our ethos and what
we stand for now I've taken around in a
linear way and that's the way say a
project might evolve but actually
they're all echo with each other the
strategist and the pioneer resonate the
steward and the genius do actually
there's the kind of you know the steward
also has a role to say we've got to take
this genius seriously otherwise we're
all stuffed and so on the peacemaker is
looking at what actually is but the
Oracle is looking at what is really
deeply yeah for me this role of the
Oracle off of again bringing us to the
to that multidimensionality of yeah it's
more the present moment than time
because time is yes meeting yeah yeah
and that that at the same time like I
love that early on you mentioned scale
linking and like this this which has
been such a insightful notion for me in
my thinking about how to how to create
planetary health or systemic health
across all those from personal to to
family to community to by region to
planet
and this transformational power that is
in understanding that everything we do
is an intervention but everything we
experience runs in fast and in slow
cycles at the same time and we have to
kind of pay attention how our
interventions make sense in the shortest
cycles and and the longer cycles and
yeah it's yet another like to some
extent the mapping of the world system
model connects trans contextually 12
nodes of key elements of a viable system
that we need to consider at minimum and
but it sort of does so more in a kind of
play sea way yeah but I find that this
panicky loop in resilience theory does
nicely is to remind how those patterns
of connected issues in place physically
also run at different speeds and and how
it's so critical to do everything in
perfect timing if you do the wrong thing
or if you if you do the right thing at
the wrong time nobody nobody listens and
you get frustrated and you have to try
again 10 years later or 30 years later
yeah yeah I mean it's you know to me
it's amazing me having this conversation
after what have we been around for 20
years now you know I mean you know since
finto
I don't know seems a long time no it's
actually a wonderful 12 years we met 12
years is it 2007 yeah I came across the
poster of the original systems of course
mm-hmm
put on with me yeah in tidying up the
lab here so yeah so that now obviously
if you look at wisdom there are many
other wisdom methods and traditions
clearly there are other ways of looking
at the earth humans
there are all kinds of systems thinking
he things to patent patent language and
stuff there and you know we've mapped
out other futures methods and so on and
there are all kinds of conflict
resolution psychology and this is what
so but our claim is that this is you
know it's not the only motor car in town
where it's a damn good model hmm it
drives nicely so I don't try you know
and there are very few of them around so
you know we do with more well it does it
it doesn't only it isn't only generative
in terms of the process of engaging we
either one of those five methods in
particular process of engaging with a
focus on a place with a purpose
sequentially with all of them will
transform the people who engage on that
yes it will it will both transform their
full awareness of the issue there the
question like the the system in question
or the question in question M but it but
I think more than that because as you do
so together it actually builds
relationship in it and it reap a turns
and yes and that's why I think it's
powerful because it demonstrates what it
tries to generate which is that the very
act of engagement is an act of reap a
Turing we don't need to rethink the
future and then start doing it by
rethinking of planning model yeah we are
already doing it in in that process and
and of course particularly if you do it
with people all the time which which is
this there's almost at nauseam theme
that runs through regenerative cultures
the living the questions together that
that I sort of start with and and then
repeat yeah a lot that's that's one of
the same
that bill is being a being what I'm
working with him on but the the whole
problem that the the level of which many
of these challenges come out that
they're sort of future stewards in
similar levels is people and not a
coherent group hmm
he doesn't he doesn't the that we
develop some of these tools they're all
in one sense developed in in communities
or corporations well one could have
people around for a while and they could
appear more than once yeah and yet we
seem to have this kind of you know
gathering of interested parties and
you've got a day to put them to
something and then they never lose the
problem it's like it's sharing a method
but it doesn't share an experience of
the power of the method over time
because that I noticed this more and
more in terms of designing educational
experiences or venturing into bringing
people together so they can do something
transformative together if you only do
that once
it it has a little inspiring effect it
builds human relationships you have all
sorts of unforeseen ripples come from
those meetings that might be
transformative but if you want the
actual issues to transform and the
people to learn you need to bring people
into some form of action learning cycle
and yeah that's what this this this
quintet does really would do really well
if you if you could convene the same
group of people that leaders quest
managers can be in once and for a day or
two and over a year five times and each
time they work with these different
methods but the issue and in between
their deepen their dialogue and their
reflection and and then then you really
have transformative projects growing out
of it and even better if you if you just
work rather than work with disparate
groups working with people in place that
I mean that's what I'm so passionate
about
for 2020 now I can see that that that
that is the the takes the place of the
organization or the corporation that the
place becomes the co hearing factor in
in the engagement with which which means
that there are people who are consistent
in their engagement but also they can be
comings and goings as well you see this
is where I it's for me yet another
reason why I keep on the one hand being
somewhat scared was my own courage to
try to work by originally again with the
whole may your consistent but at the
same time that's what brought me here
eight years ago of under understanding
after all these years at the community
scale and working with Vint on and
intentional communities eco villages and
transition towns that so much can be
done at the community scale but to
really create the whole system's design
enabling constraints together that that
make for the emergence of health and
wholeness in the system you need to step
up to the bioregional scale and and then
also running a process like this over
time with some people coming in some
people coming out with but with a core
group that got runs through the whole
process and again working with when you
work at the local the micro level you
can create communities of interest you
can gather the usual suspects but the
minute you step to the bioregional scale
you have to engage all the players you
have to work across sectors and and kind
of face the complexity and and and I
think that that's where I'm really kind
of wanting to put my energies over the
next couple of years of testing out
these type of processes at the bio
regional scale and data and
be the big challenge for us little guys
is is that that's a huge overhead yes
getting that funded like stain because
then the thing is it's not just I mean
it's actually peanuts compared to the
scale of the problem and the amount of
resources available but yeah the heroes
the horizon-1 culture doesn't get it if
if local governments plus locally
important larger corporations would
understand that that's their way of risk
managing the future and building climate
resilience to finance these processes
then then they could happen everywhere
because it's what I've also realized
it's not enough to be able to pay the
people who are facilitating and like
really if you want to engage people in
building a transformative community that
through running through a process like
that also transforms and therefore reap
patterns you have to somehow resource
that all the people the participants to
not have to be out of pocket to be
taking part in what you're offering yeah
and maybe they contribute a little bit
to have some form of energetic
engagement but but also to be given time
to reflect on that process and prepare
between one and another face to face
element by by staying engaged whether
it's through online conversations and so
on and so forth and and and so part of
like I've been starting to look into
writing sort of grant applications for
these kind of processes and really you
want to be able to run with groups of 40
50 60 people that you can invite to
these and can cover part of their
organizational time wherever they work
in which of the four sectors and yeah
just stay engaged with the process and
yeah and then you would have a group
that would over a year or a year and a
half running through a process like that
really come up with
every patterning of the future of that
region yeah that's the well I I think on
a personal note if I was your age I'd
still be up for it but it's my age I'm
afraid I'm gonna have to be part of the
meta system and feed stuff in you know
saying to the guys at h3 uni look we've
got out a much more modest ambition for
h3 uni because you know we basically
just three old guys and a few friends
you know you know that was that that was
the peacemaker speaking you know let's
just calm down and look at who we are
and actually where we are and what we
can really do that's got some leverage
and I think this is what I've shared
with you here is part of that sort of
thrust yeah and what and to just that
excites me is just thinking about you
know how can I put it with this approach
here now I think I could start to write
your book with a slightly different way
please we need many more expressions of
the impulse behind it and because each
one speaks differently to different
people and yeah I think the one that the
book you bringing out is is a massive
contribution and well it's it's it's
still upstream but it's like um it's not
fashionable to give great value to ideas
but I think ideas of but in their time
at the right time they're very powerful
and we need we need some of the ideas
like you know the way you pick up on
them
on present-moment multidimensionality
and you know I was listening to some of
what you were saying just now and I
certainly had a flash and thought blimey
that's almost like Henry talks you know
it's it's all rubbing off gradually
between us you know I mean Henry's been
between you and and Henry have been
really the two people that have deeply
deeply shaped the the way I think and
yeah
other people like I mean Brian Goodwin
and Stefan Harding have also shaped very
much what I think about in the the Union
what am I thinking but the actual
pattern of thinking and shifting is
something that that's why I find it so
fascinating that that Henry and Gertie
the Gertie and approaching is working
with that sort of phenom a logical
hermeneutical approach then you the way
of all the techniques that you've just
explained that they're h3 unius
stewarding and has shared through the
website and how people can can work with
these these five methodologies and
processes and then to find yet another
third group of elders that that have
also somehow drunk from the same
fountains and through yeah yeah and then
there are the elders in Carroll Sanford
and and and the Genesis group and I find
it fascinating that they're all connect
and I'm I'm just continuing to this this
there's something going on like the
bottom of it eventually
exactly can you just just briefly before
I am stop the recording say a couple of
things about your book and what it's
about and when it's coming out um yeah
well system's thinking for a turbulent
world is a rather ambitious attempt to
to portage
there's some powerful theories that need
to be in my view embedded in practice
and in our academic world theory and
practice or rather kept separate so the
worst case scenario is it's a book that
will not be read either by theorists or
practitioners but the designs that
you're getting from your little
experiment with your network suggest
that maybe there is a population of
people who really want to bring good
good theory new ways of looking at the
world and good practice like what we're
applying it to together
so I hope it's a contribution to that
and to me that's a kind of a paradigm
shift that I've been obsessed with for
some time so the reader in search of new
ways of thinking I'm just reading from
what will probably be on the back cover
will be introduced to concepts new to
systems thinking that integrate systems
thinking and futures thinking the
concept of anticipated present moment a
p.m. serves as a basis for learning the
cognitive skills that better enable
navigation through turbulent times a key
personal and team practice this
participative read paddling which is the
basis for transformative innovation this
practice is aided by numerous revisions
the siltation
hang on that's sorry about two richly
washing answer it I'm still on my call I
hope to finish very soon then I'll cook
by very important them more than but
most important things in life cooking up
meal for the family that's right yeah my
turn yeah yeah now this is this is the
interesting thing to the reader is
guided through the unfolding of the
ideas and practices with a narrative
based on the metaphor research or
trading the tradition of Oxfordian found
in Far East and traditional
consciousness practice yeah I really
loved reading it and for what I shared
with people there's a lot of resonance
to it and I think it just has really
powerful concepts like there is simply
black term it's I don't know if I think
it emerged between you and Bill somehow
the the future potential of the present
moment yes if you really sit with just
that in it yeah you really have to sit
with it but it's powerful and and then
in because it also it's it's almost like
one of those thence fixed it if you're
about to react against what somebody has
just said then if you think future
potential at the present moment you can
like like Krishnamurti saying there's
there's a world between the moment that
you see the tiger and you respond to
seeing a tiger yes running away in fear
or realizing the tiger isn't hungry and
marveling at its beauty and makes all
the difference and and and so there's
that it's a sort of metaphorical way
that I understand the future potential
of the present moment that we can by
Reaper sieving the presence shape the
future
and and byberry perceiving how we are in
the presence how we are in relationship
with other and self and now and future
generations yeah I was always struck um
you know some talk that John Bennett
gave is too far in the past to recollect
properly but it was something like um it
was a lecture on the future and he
started by saying all we have is now
yeah disgust I think that's a perfect
place to stop that regeneration is
actually exactly what happens now always
and you know just just quickly Daniel
the stages of the book from the
exploration are the the seeking of the
Ox is healing our fragmented world you
know we actually need the Ox the Ox is a
symbol of the unknown thing we need this
the second finding the tracks is
rehabilitating observer we've actually
forgotten ourselves in the process of
our last 300 years of scientific
development and so on the third step is
the first glimpse of the ox which is the
chapter II perceiving the future
actually we've got trapped in in a time
assumption that's become unhelpful we
need to look at it differently then the
fourth step catching the Ox is the
anticipatory systems are different which
is the introduction of the APM and then
the fifth stage of taming the Ox
is cultivating decision integrity is
that leaders enter decision is learning
and the notion of undecidable questions
choose fascinating and then the chapter
six riding the Ox home is the step to
the co creative way that we need to do
this together and we need to practice of
reap reap patterning and then the
seventh stage is the Ox out of sight the
self alone the chapters called
transforming in the now perception
within the present moment just mentioned
and then chapter eight is natural
systems thinking it's it's it's that the
in this case the the the guy who's been
looking for the Ox no longer is
concerned about the Ox he just wanders
into town and things get better yes
that's the there are ten stages if you
look it up but the original one way back
in Taoism with eight stages so I went
with the original Taoist so anyway it
was been quite late you seven o'clock in
there I better catch if I want to catch
my daughter before she go to see ya nine
I need so thank you so much I'm just
going to start recording now thank you
yeah well